Guide to the Vladimir and Véra Nabokov publishing correspondence, 1945-1977.
Nabokov, Vladimir and Véra publishing correspondence, 1945-1977
- Series IV. Outgoing Correspondence from Véra Nabokov 1949-1977
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, January 23, 1960 to February 12, 1960. (Box 5, Folder 16)
    6 TLS, in French, concerning the film rights, foreign publication rights and accounting for Lolita and other works (including Conclusive Evidence, Invitation, Laughter in the Dark, Pnin, and The Defense). Asks whether Olympia has the right to publish a pocketbook edition of Lolita without consulting VN (an issue that will become especially contentious).
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, February 6, 1960 to April 27, 1960. (Box 5, Folder 17)
    6 TLS, 1 TLS fragment, in French with some English, concerning various contractual matters, including growing dispute between VN and Girodias over Olympia's pocketbook edition of Lolita. Outlines faults with the translation of the short story That in Aleppo Once, and thanks Ergaz for the excellent letter that she has written to Playboy
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, April 28, 1960 to June 9, 1960. (Box 5, Folder 18)
    7 TLS, 1 AL, in French, concerning various contractual, translation and accounting matters. Texts mentioned include Sebastian Knight, Lolita, Invitation and The Defense.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, June 10, 1960 to July 8, 1960. (Box 5, Folder 19)
    6 TLS, in French with some English, outlining problems with the French translation of Spring in Fialta, further contract woes with Girodias, the "amusing" discovery of 5 pirated editions of Lolita currently circulating in Lebanon.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, July 17, 1960 to September 10, 1960. (Box 5, Folder 20)
    8 TLS, in French and English, re the contract with Gallimard for The Defense, translation of Spring in Fialta by Berger, misunderstanding surrounding SUR's payments, and pocketbook dispute with Olympia.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, September 19, 1960 to February 15, 1961. (Box 5, Folder 21)
    8 TLS, 1 autograph note, in French and English, concerning the action taken against the pirated Lebanese editions of Lolita, litigation planned with Olympia, and sale of film rights to Laughter in the Dark, sold to Lombrosos.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, March 2, 1961 to April 13, 1961. (Box 5, Folder 22)
    4 TLS, mainly concerning the planned proceedings against Olympia.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, July 8, 1961 to September 15, 1961. (Box 5, Folder 23)
    8 TLS, in French, regarding the film adaptation of Laughter in the Dark and disputes with Olympia, old and new. Autograph postscript to 7.26.61. "Confidential" mention of a new novel, to be published in 1962 (Pale Fire).
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, October 15, 1961 to November 9, 1961. (Box 5, Folder 24)
    12 TLS in French with some English, concerning various contractual, translation and accounting matters, including the pirated Mexican edition of Laughter in the Dark, and an offer by "Le club français" to publish short story La visite au musée. Asks for news of legal proceedings against Olympia and wonders if it would be good to warn lawyer, Castelain, about "wiliness" of his opponent.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, November 18, 1961 to December 17, 1961. (Box 5, Folder 25)
    7 TLS, in French and English (sometimes a mix of both, as in 11.18.61), concerning the pocketbook contract with Gallimard, the film adaptation of Laughter in the Dark
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, December 17, 1961 to February 9, 1962. (Box 5, Folder 26)
    7 TLS, in French, regarding some contractual and accounting matters (including the ongoing problems with New Directions over Sebastian Knight), as well as the difficulty of translating Pale Fire into French and the importance of finding a translator who knows both French and English, and the release of Kubrick's adaptation Lolita (the only European distributor Kubrick has found is a German company).
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, February 14, 1962 to March 2, 1962. (Box 5, Folder 27)
    7 TLS, in French and Russian, concerning the needed re-translation of The Defense into French, distribution of Lolita (film) in Europe, the French publication of Pale Fire, Harris-Kubrick's refusal to consider the release of a "Lolita song", and one of Véra's backhanded criticisms: "I abstain from all criticism [of a novel Le sang du ciel] since you [Ergaz] tell me that you love this book" (2.14.62). Long autograph postscript to 2.14.62.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, March 4, 1962 to March 27, 1962. (Box 5, Folder 28)
    7 TLS, in French, regarding the legal proceedings against Olympia (which VN has dropped, having become the defendant), ongoing difficulties with New Directions over Sebastian Knight, an unauthorized citation of Lolita in a Vogue perfume ad, and other contractual and translation matters.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, April 4, 1962 to May 10, 1962. (Box 5, Folder 29)
    9 TLS, in French, regarding payment to Olympia before the legal settlement has been confirmed, a proposed BBC television dramatization of Laughter in the Dark, the continuing attempts to sign a contract with Gallimard for Sebastian Knight, and various possible contracts for Pale Fire.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, May 17, 1962 to July 28, 1962. (Box 5, Folder 30)
    8 TLS, 1 autograph note, in French, regarding the contract with New Directions for Sebastian Knight, the foreign publication of Lolita and Pale Fire, as well as proposed interview with Paris Presse (Véra outlines the conditions on which VN will agree to the interview).
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, August 11, 1962 to October 7, 1962. (Box 5, Folder 31)
    6 TLS, in French, regarding the difficult contract with New Directions for Sebastian Knight, the Gallimard contract for Pale Fire, Indian translations of Lolita, and the slow progress being made on the film adaptation of Laughter in the Dark.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, October 10, 1962 to December 5, 1962. (Box 5, Folder 32)
    7 TLS, in French, regarding various pocketbook editions of Lolita, the Lumbroso adaptation of Laughter, publication of some of VN's short storys, and search for translator for Pale Fire (VN wants a Canadian who knows both English and French well).
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, January 12, 1963 to February 19, 1963. (Box 5, Folder 33)
    7 TLS, in French, regarding various pocketbook editions of Lolita (including an unauthorized edition by Gumerus), the Lumbroso adaptation of Laughter (which is not proceeding), and the translation of Pale Fire. Véra has been in bed with the flu and apologizes for the bad state of her correspondence. She notes the British success of the film Lolita.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, February 22, 1963 to June 7, 1963. (Box 5, Folder 34)
    7 TLS, in French, with some English, concerning the contract with Gumerus for a pocketbook edition of Lolita in Finnish and other such contractual and accounting matters, the translation of Pale Fire (VN finds Girard's sample very good), as well as a possible new ban on Olympia Press books.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, June 19, 1963 to September 13, 1963. (Box 5, Folder 35)
    7 TLS, in French with some English, concerning various contractual and accounting matters, outlining in detail VN's dealings with New Directions (this following a letter sent by New Directions to Gallimard, with whom VN is currently negotiating for the French publication of Sebastian Knight).
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, October 13, 1963 to February 25, 1964. (Box 5, Folder 36)
    8 TLS, in French, concerning contract with a Turkish firm for the publication of Lolita, continued problems with New Directions, translation of Pale Fire (Coindreau's irascibility), and relations with the Lumbrosos.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, March 7, 1964 to June 25, 19634. (Box 5, Folder 37)
    5 TLS, 2 autograph notes, in French with some English, concerning The New Yorker's plans to publish The Defense in 2 consecutive numbers ( new venture), and suggesting that Gallimard time its republication of the novel accordingly. Discusses other contractual and accounting matters (regarding The Gift, Eugene Onegin, and a story), and asks after the action taken in response to an article in L'europeo.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, July 22, 1964 to October 12, 1964. (Box 5, Folder 38)
    7 TLS, in French, concerning various contractual and accounting matters (regarding The Gift and Lolita), the publication of an extract of Lolita in an anthology, and the news that Olympia has lost its right to publish.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko and Thérèse Mairesse, November 1, 1964 to December 23, 1964. (Box 5, Folder 39)
    7 TLS, 1 autograph postcard, in French and English, concerning the Yugoslav publication rights for Lolita, the Lumbrosos, the translation of Pale Fire, and continuing difficulties with Olympia. Thanks Schébéko for "an amusing version of the Girodias affair" (12.23.64).
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko and Thérèse Mairesse, January 20, 1965 to February 9, 1965. (Box 5, Folder 40)
    7 TLS, concerning French publication of Eugene Onegin and other accounting matters, proposed acquisition of the film rights to Laughter in the Dark by Les Films de Jeudi (run either by a M. Braunberger or Bromberger - Véra isn't sure).
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, February 14, 1965 to April 25, 1965. (Box 5, Folder 41)
    6 TLS, in French, concerning the choice of translator for The Gift (finally given to Girard/ Coindreau, with VN's approval despite his description of Coindreau as a "vilain charactère"), necessity for VN to see the proofs of Pale Fire, as he is concerned that Coindreau will refuse to incorporate VN's corrections.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Doussia Ergaz and Marie Schébéko, May 9, 1965 to August 26, 1965. (Box 5, Folder 42)
    6 TLS, with copy of TL sent to a Mr. Cottakis, in French and English, concerning contractual matters re Lolita, and the dispute with Olympia, especially the withholding of all payments to Olympia.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko and Gallimard, September 2, 1965 to October 16, 1965. (Box 5, Folder 43)
    8 TLS, in French with some English, concerning the proofs of Pale Fire, an interview with France-Observateur that VN finds impossible to give, the publication of The Eye in the US and potentially in France.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, October 21, 1965 to November 20, 1965. (Box 5, Folder 44)
    4 TLS, in French, with attached TL to Mme. Duconget and typed corrections to Pale Fire, re the Russian publication of Lolita, the proofs of Pale Fire, and the memoirs of Count Ignatieff.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, November 23, 1965 to January 17, 1966. (Box 5, Folder 45)
    5 TLS, 1 TL (copy), in French, concerning lack of publicity surrounding publication of Pale Fire (cites a short piece in Les Lettres Françaises wondering when Pale Fire, praised by Mary McCarthy, will appear in France), but emphasizing that VN has no interest in what reviewers say of the novel. Mention new proceedings against Girodias.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, January 27, 1966 to March 4, 1966. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    7 TLS, in French and English, regarding the problems surrounding a possible Russian edition of Lolita, a point of accounting confusion for Véra, the payment of American taxes, and the French publication of The Eye.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, March 10, 1966 to May 28, 1966. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    7 TLS, in French and English, concerning the French publication of Despair (newly translated from Russian into adapted English version), contract with Gallimard for The Eye, VN's complaint that French publishers are far less generous with their authors than other European publishers. Postscript note to 5.24.66 lauding service at their Chinciano hotel, and noting that VN has caught some exciting butterflies.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, June 10, 1966 to August 29, 1966. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    6 TLS, 1 autograph note, in French and English, concerning the film adaptation of Laughter in the Dark (still not completed, or indeed, begun), a "poor" M. Roychowdhury (a publisher) who Véra says has been taken advantage of, the American publication in Russian of Lolita, and the difficulty of buying things in Italian village stores.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, October 5, 1966 to October 18, 1966. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    4 TLS, 1 autograph note, in French and English, regarding various foreign publication contracts for Lolita (some of which are expiring), affairs with Roychowdhury, and VN's revision of the French translation of The Gift, which he says contains some massive blunders. An autograph note asking Schébéko to forward a letter to Vogue declining a request for a short suspense or detective story.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, November 2, 1966 to December 29, 1966. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    5 TLS, with attached autograph note (probably the agent's), in French, regarding some accounting matters, the revision of The Gift, the possibility of republishing Bend Sinister, the legal proceedings against Olympia, and the translation of The Eye.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, January 9, 1967 to February 18, 1967. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    5 TLS, 1 of which is typed on a copy of a letter sent to Dr. Bloch, in French and English, explaining enclosures (of corrections to The Gift and The Eye), offers from foreign publishers for Lolita, and the publication of expanded version of Conclusive Evidence, (Speak, Memory). Mentions a "fan-letter" from Robbe-Grillet about Pale Fire.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, March 13, 1967 to July 14, 1967. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    5 TLS, in French, concerning various contractual and publication matters (especially re The Gift). Expresses sorrow at the death of Doussia Ergaz, and encloses a check to pay for flowers.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, July 25, 1967 to October 3, 1967. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    6 TLS, in French with some English, asking after the proofs for The Gift and agreeing to the prepublication of a chapter of The Gift in The Paris Review, wondering why VN's works sell terribly in France, and why Gallimard and Grasset don't do more to advertise these books, and announcing the publication of a Russian translation of Lolita in the US. Véra notes that her husband has not yet received answers to letters written to Girard and Gallimard. She explains that VN is "touchy" on this subject, believing that "all his letters should receive answers" (10.3.67).
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, October 25, 1967 to December 30, 1967. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    6 TLS in French and English, regarding the publication of some short stories, and outlining VN's dissatisfaction with Girard, who not only refuses to respond to VN's letters but has not incorporated VN's suggestions with regard to the verse and word game sections of The Gift. VN is particularly annoyed that the list of errata has not been included with the novel, and that he has not been given credit for his translation work.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, January 11, 1968 to March 15, 1968. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    5 TLS, in French and English, noting VN's change of American publishers (from Putnam's to McGraw-Hill, which will publish am English translation of King, Queen, Knave), and the failure of Olympia's appeal. As a result of this judgment, all of the royalties held in escrow now revert to VN, who must now attempt to find a new (and respectable) publisher for Lolita
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, April 17, 1968 to August 3, 1968. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    6 TLS, with attached correspondence between Véra, Weidenfeld & Nicolson, and the agent for an Icelandic publisher, in French and English, concerning a possible Icelandic edition of Lolita, expressing irritation over the "hours" of work VN has had to put in correction Gallimard's translations, and in recovering "from the vexations every time he had to deal with M. Girard" (6.15.68), and discussing to as yet to begun film adaptation of Laughter in the Dark (now to be made with Richard Burton and Anna Karina). Discusses other foreign offers for Lolita (especially from India and Czechoslovakia).
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, August 26, 1968 to October 10, 1968. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    8 TLS, in French and English, regarding the Malayalam contract for Lolita (including some derogatory comments about Indians and Pakistanis), a possible contract with Gallimard for King, Queen, Knave, and asking after the status of the Czech and Slovak editions of Lolita (Véra does not wish to write to the publishers directly because of the recent Soviet occupation).
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko and D. Develdère, November 4, 1968 to February 3, 1969. (Box 6, Folder 13)
    6 TLS, one of which is typed on a letter sent to Françoise Gaillard of Gallimard, in French and English, regarding the problems in Czechoslovakia, and a possible contract with Gallimard for King, Queen, Knave. VN would like to wait before signing this contract to see how Gallimard handles the launch of The Eye, and stipulates that he control choice of translator for King, Queen, Knave. Notes upcoming publication of Ada by McGraw-Hill and Weidenfeld & Nicolson, and agrees to give Gallimard first shot at Ada, while asking Gallimard to consider giving VN a more favorable contract than those signed for Pale Fire and The Eye.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko and D. Develdère, February 4, 1969 to May 30, 1969. (Box 6, Folder 14)
    7 TLS, in French, concerning contracts for Lolita with Dilia (Czechoslovakia), two Yugoslavian firms and a Swiss firm, as well as changes to the Gallimard contract for King, Queen, Knave. Véra has not been well.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko and D. Develdère, June 2, 1969 to August 13, 1969. (Box 6, Folder 15)
    6 TLS, in French and English, concerning the Finnish translation of Lolita, the contracts for Czechoslovakia, and negotiations to publish Lolita. in Yugoslavia and Mexico/Spain. VN is "frankly annoyed" by the poor sales of his books in France, and complains of the hostility with which French translators treat his suggestions. He sets base conditions for contract with Gallimard for Ada, among which are a large advance, payment for his help with translation, and adequate budget for publicity. Includes autograph postcard, posted.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko and D. Develdère, September 1, 1969 to October 10, 1969. (Box 6, Folder 16)
    7 TLS, in French and English, concerning various contractual and accounting matters, especially a contract for the French publication of Ada, which VN considers his greatest work (the VNs are looking to sign with a firm other than Gallimard, perhaps Flammarion).
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, October 22, 1969 to December 7, 1969. (Box 6, Folder 17)
    6 TLS, 1 autograph note, in French and English, concerning foreign publication of Lolita (in Spanish, Portuguese, Czech), as well as the contract for the French publication of Ada. Autograph postscript to 12.7.69.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko and D. Develdère, December 9, 1970 to March 18, 1970. (Box 6, Folder 18)
    7 TLS, 1 autograph note, in French, re: the publication of Lolita with various foreign firms (Dilia, Prins, Zarvanos, Grijalbo and firms in Iceland, Japan, and Yugoslavia.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, April 8, 1970 to November 23, 1970. (Box 6, Folder 19)
    7 TLS, 2 autograph notes, in French and English, concerning various contractual matters, including publication of Mary by McGraw-Hill, substitution in the negotiations with the Icelandic publishers of Laughter in the Dark for Lolita, as well as the French translation (by Magnane) of King, Queen, Knave (no longer to be published by Gallimard)
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, November 27, 1970 to February 15, 1971. (Box 6, Folder 20)
    7 TLS, in French, concerning Fayard's offer for Mary (which VN accepts), the translation of King, Queen, Knave by Magnane (of which VN approves, despite some errors), and the couple's incredulity that Grasset should have sold only 1 copy of Laughter over a 2 year period. Postscript autograph to 11.21.70
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko and D. Develdère, February 15, 1971 to July 12, 1971. (Box 6, Folder 21)
    7 TLS, in French and English, concerning various foreign contracts for Lolita (Japan, Greece, in Portuguese, Czechoslovakia and Yugoslavia). Véra finds reason to extend the contract with the Czechs as the political situation is so dire, but cannot see why the Yugoslavians should be granted the same. She is also amused to see that Grasset has suddenly sold 81 copies of Laughter in the Dark.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, July 23, 1971 to October 22, 1971. (Box 6, Folder 22)
    7 TLS, in French and English, regarding the contract for a paperback edition of Lolita with Gallimard, the Yugoslavian publication of Lolita, the translation of Ada (which VN has yet to see), and Gallimard's interest in Poems and Problems.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, October 27, 1971 to January 5, 1972. (Box 6, Folder 23)
    6 TLS, in French and English, regarding the foreign publication of Lolita (in Japan), possible pirating of Lolita. Autograph postscript to 12.20.71.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, January 26, 1972 to April 10, 1972. (Box 6, Folder 24)
    7 TLS, in French and English, expressing embarassment over the number of copies (18) of King, Queen, Knave sent the VNs by Gallimard and Clairouin, and regarding various contractual and accounting matters, including the paperback contract with Gallimard for VN's works, and interest in the film rights to The Defense.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, April 21, 1972 to June 17, 1972. (Box 6, Folder 25)
    5 TLS (including a copy), 1 autograph note, in French and English, concerning the slow pace of the Ada translation, the eventual publication of VN's new novel (Transparent Things, whose completion is noted in 4.21.72), the paperback contract with Gallimard, and the contracts with Kersovani (Yugoslavia).
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, July 24, 1972 to October 27, 1972. (Box 6, Folder 26)